foreign
welcome everyone it's January 3rd 2023
we're in active bookstream number
001.04 on governing continuous
transformation off to you blue
great so we are the active inference
Institute uh and this discussion is over
governing continuous transformation this
is a recorded and an archives live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve upon our work
uh we are a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
you can reach us on social media at all
of these uh different links here all
backgrounds and perspectives are welcome
to discuss and contribute to this work
and we will be following good video
etiquette for live streams if you would
like to get in touch to participate in a
future.0 live stream or um one of the
upcoming discussions please reach out to
us via social media or email
um and again our links so today we are
going to cover section 1.4 so we're just
going to go kind of over where we are in
the book uh the keywords and then the
different
subjects and um things that we pulled
out of this section
so just to start off we will uh maybe
just introduce ourselves I am blue I am
a long time Institute participant and um
an independent researcher in New Mexico
and I'll pass it to Daniel
I'm Daniel I'm a researcher and
Institute participant all Pastor Tyler
I'm Tyler I'm a dow researcher and
practitioner in California
so um is there any introductory comments
or do you guys just want to jump right
into it
jump in okay here we go
so this is the section that covers the
free energy principle and that's also
the title of this chapter and I think
the first key word on our keyword slides
um so we've pulled out a lot of these uh
keywords I mean we pulled them out
um they weren't highlighted by Bijan or
selected by him at all and this is just
kind of the the topics that we thought
that would be better to dive deeper into
for a more thorough understanding of the
material presented in this chapter
um and we will this is not like a final
word this is maybe just an introductory
perspective and our take on what's maybe
happening in this um in this chapter not
a review so we're definitely open to
correction and updating our our model of
this model
all right uh so abstract Tyler do you
want to read this first section first
sure so the free energy principle is the
first order principle of police action
empowering self-organization FTP
commands a generative process of active
inference dedicated to minimizing the
information theoretical mathematic
mathematical difference between top-down
predictions and action generated bottom
of student lab in pursuit of minimizing
error surprise entropy
the power of Estonian academic presence
is fundamentally four-fold is a pure
belief setting in Dynamic and
non-stationary environments we added
inference agent carries out episode
exploration to account for uncertainty
by making inferences in Bayes optimal
fashion
the reward signal is so characteristic
of reinforcement learning is removed and
finally active inference sets the
collaborative human machine uh AI
potential so integral to the
multi-intelligence firm as the
mathematical expression of beliefs the
form of probabilities provides the very
common denominator to line humans with
issues
wow big of true
uh okay and um the author goes on to say
there are only two distinctions that
matter what is known and unknown and
what is in our control and what is not
there are four states active action
internal firm resources sensory
perception and external unknown and
hidden behind the Markov blanket
according to free energy governance free
energy principle powered AI which he
uses here this capital A in lower case I
to mean active inference so free energy
principle powered active inference is
the future site of organizational
becoming
so we can unpack that I guess starting
with um this claim which was in the
abstract itself so
um maybe we don't need to reread it or
was it exactly stated there maybe not oh
yeah four-fold
so
the four claims we'll just start off
this first one
um the power of prestonian actins is
fundamentally four-fold it is a pure
belief-based setting in Dynamic and
non-stationary environments so what does
that mean or like what is prestonian
active in France so maybe we want to
just step back a little bit and talk
about the fvp
and the the definition or explanation
that Bijan picked out for this chapter
is the free energy principle stems from
the idea that living systems can be
distinguished from other self-organizing
systems because they actively avoid
deleterious phase transitions by
bounding the entropy of their sensory
and physical States under the fep to be
alive simply means to revisit a bounded
set of states with a high probability
um and that's from this 2019
um Badcock LL paper and this image is
from Kirchoff at Al 2018.
um and I always like this like when I
think about life and self-organized
organizing systems
um it kind of this picture just really
like speaks to what it is to kind of be
self-organizing
like a hierarchical
um scale so and this like revisiting a
bounded set of states with a high
probability kind of speaks to the
non-equilibrium steady state density
that is like a constraint of life we
kind of have to live within you know
like a certain temperature range a
certain you know glucose range and all
life has like an optimal range of states
that they stay in but like if your fever
gets too high like if a temperature goes
too high or too low like you will
dissipate so you revisit
um this bounded set of states with a
high probability and that's kind of your
non-equilibrium of steady state density
do you guys have any comments here on
the FTP and self-organizing maybe
okay if one comment this is a via
positiva it's describing what the fep is
but we could look back to those four
claims and think about what this is not
the Via negativa so rather than being
belief based in Dynamic settings and
adaptive autonomous agents it might be a
framework oriented around some sort of
static or perennial understanding of the
world the second Point rather than being
centered around epistemic exploration
and the value of reducing uncertainty
and gaining information hearing New
Perspectives it could be oriented around
pragmatic or utility value which ties
very closely to the third point which is
that a framework contrary to active
inference might Center a reward function
that Maps different states of the agent
or the organization or the world to some
sort of reward function which is the
heart of reward learning and then the
fourth Point um also kind of ties in
rather than thinking about uh ecosystem
of shared intelligence
intermediated by composable Frameworks
like active inference we might be
looking for like the one framework to
Simply rule them all and therefore not
think about the human machine or human
Human Relationships as collaborative and
emergent but rather just be looking for
the one computer we're just going to
turn it on the business is going to run
thank you
awesome
so uh getting into active inference a
little bit more so we're kind of
unpacking here we're going to unpack
slowly these like four claims
um and so forstonian active inference or
fep powered active
um so in active inference there are four
states this is what Bijan claims active
action internal firm resources sensory
perception and external which is unknown
and hidden behind the markup blanket
um and Bijan quotes Christian here and
says inactive inference the agent makes
choices based on its belief about states
of the world and not based on the value
of the states and so that speaks to what
Daniel was maybe just mentioning about
reinforcement learning and we'll we'll
start to unravel reinforcement learning
a little bit more but where
reinforcement learning is really kind of
driven by that pragmatic value function
um
active inference is driven by your
beliefs about the world so not how much
value can you gain out of moving left or
moving right but like I fundamentally
believe that I should
move right because that's my policy
that I've you know that I operate on so
um yeah
all right and
um
in this where where are these claims
start to be unpacked in the paper
uh Bijan says one could argue that
nearly all physical sciences can be
reduced to a Metrology in service of
confirming a variant of the principle of
least action this is important because
it means that physics does not offer any
ground truth it is just search for
measurements that endorse and
appropriately formulated prediction
based upon a variation or principle and
this quotes a first in 2019 paper I
don't know that paper off the top of my
head
um but as funny as I said Bijan says and
then I started reading it I'm like no
Carl said this it's like a very um this
sounds very much like something that
would come out of a Carl paper
um okay and so what is this principle of
least action we've talked about this a
lot before in many different uh live
streams but I looked it up just for like
what is like a really easy simple way
that I could explain it and you know a
minute or less
um and I found this definition on
scholarpedia
that says a true dynamical trajectory of
a system between an initial and final
configuration in a specified time is
found by imagining all possible
trajectories that the system could
conceivably take Computing the action
which is a function of the trajectory
and just as a reminder a functional is
like a function of a function so
Computing the action a functional is a
trajectory for each of these
trajectories and selecting one that
makes the action locally stationary
traditionally called least true
trajectories are those that have the
least action and so this is like the
laziness the lazy Society everybody
makes the The Lazy choice right so so
like the true trajectory is the one
where you kind of just stay put Daniel
do you have a comment here yes although
on the previous slide we looked at the
particular partition where action states
are the outgoing dependencies and here
we see action again with the principle
of least action but importantly
to abide by a principle of least action
isn't simply to take the lowest energy
action or the least movement it's more
akin to a conservation law like the
total energy is conserved of potential
plus kinetic when the ball falls off the
platform so that means that there's a
path of least action with the ball
dropping now that is not the path of
least movement but it's a path of least
action given an initial setup because
the total energy is conserved and so
we're interested in Paths of least
action
over the particular partitioned States
internal external and blanket States and
so it's a little bit like um
not just simply confusing but least
action can include the selection of very
energetic or risky behaviors
that's cool so and just to kind of like
maybe tie that to a real world example I
think about like the principle of least
action like I prefer my body temperature
to be like 75 degrees all the time right
like do I live in the tropics no because
there's like a lot of things about
living on a tropical island that are
like not optimal for me so like I live
in New Mexico because that's like my
optimal like place but I wear a jacket
in the winter and like in the summertime
I you know wear less clothes or like
drive around in my air-conditioned car
and live in my air-conditioned house so
even though like I'm still expending
energy to maintain my physical
temperature like that is the path of
least like action for me like I I I
compensate for the change in my
equilibrium state
um through my actions
okay and
we will
talk more about energy in a minute so
unpacking this second part of the theme
the active agent carries out epistemic
exploration to account for uncertainty
by making inferences in Bayes optimal
fashion
um Okay so
like I know what Bayes optimal is or
like I think I know what Bayes optimal
is but um just to kind of like what is
Bayes optimal fashion and how do you
make inference uh in Bayes optimal
fashion and it's cool because like in a
quick Google search like I always like
to search these fundamental like things
um just to see kind of what pops up like
I think I know what bay is optimal is
and and I've pulled out this 2019 paper
like what is optimal in in optimal
inference
um and it's interesting because like
going into phase optimal I mean I think
about Bayes optimal as like minimizing
prediction error or it says here
classically optimal Bayesian inference
balances prior knowledge and ongoing
observations to identify the model with
maximum posterior probability
um and so these authors actually take
this a step further and I really enjoyed
their um but like thought process here
so they said concretely we might say
that an inference procedure is optimal
if it maximizes benefit per unit cost in
which the benefit is some monotonically
increasing function of accuracy
um but they proposed a generalization of
this approach that that kind of splits
this cost benefit curve into two
components where the first component
describes the benefit perhaps the award
the reward obtained as a function of
accuracy but then the second component
so that's the minimizing prediction
error that I was I'm speaking to earlier
right like in terms of accuracy and then
the second component describes accuracy
as a function of costs which can include
time memory and computational resources
needed to process information and I
think that this is like the fundamental
thing that I mean I might Overlook like
like I might be able to get like a a way
more accurate answer
um like you know just so say for example
like what is what is the number Pi right
and I could just say like 3.14 I could
actually go through I could say like
3.14159 like off the top of my head like
that's like the whatever number of
digits of pi that I have memorized so
like some accurate point but like I
could come to a far more accurate answer
of that if I sat there with a pencil and
a piece of paper for the entire rest of
my life doing long division right so I
could come to like some infinite number
of of
um you know units past the decimal point
and I could go on and on and on forever
but like is it worth it right like is is
it worth it in terms of like memory
effort to calculate that increasing
accuracy or should it's like 3.14 good
enough right and and so that is kind of
the thing that they're um like the
functions that they're describing here
like this benefit this two dual
component like yes we want accuracy but
we also want it to be fast or want it to
be we want to
get the maximum benefit for the minimum
resource expenditure so I like that that
they are um you know describing accuracy
as a function of the costs the effort
that goes into it
um do you guys have any comments here
okay so
um why am I going into this okay so
Tyler and I got into this long talk
about energy
um and we got into I I can't remember I
guess it's not maybe in this claim but
it was somewhere in the paper maybe I
should look and try to pull it up but we
really got into discussing energy like
what is free energy what is like kinetic
and potential energy
and what is free energy like in the fep
and we've gone to many live streams that
like dive way deeper into this
um and I think it's live stream 17 that
is the one I pointed you to Tyler that
that is um Alex Kiefer is a great like
unpacking unraveling of free energy in
that way but I think it's important here
to point out uh maybe Tyler you can pull
that quote out of the paper while I'm
I'm talking about this but I think it's
important to point out that information
theoretic entropy is different than
um thermodynamic entropy and and so in
information Theory
um and there are many times in the paper
where like the author specifically says
like we're talking about information
theoretic entropy but then it seems like
that the other kind of entropy is hinted
at and so I kind of wanted to just like
draw a line between like information
theoretic entropy and the other kind of
entropy like um the second law of
Thermodynamics thermodynamic entropy
um and these these two are are distinct
but not entirely unrelated
so information theoretic entropy um is
defined as like in if you have a
function X or some event X the negative
log of the probability of X is equal to
the information so here you can see like
the probability versus the information
is this graph on the left so
um where there's a high probability of
an event there's like low information
like
um there's a high probability that like
I will you know take a breath in my in
the next 30 seconds so like me taking a
breath in the next 30 seconds like
doesn't contain any information but like
the you guys can predict that I will
talk about
the fep and free energy governance in
the next minute
um if I start talking about like my dead
dog there's like low probability of that
like happening and so there's like maybe
a much higher level of information like
whoa where did this come from this is
way out of left field so there's more
information in like an unexpected
um claim and so you can see like a
probability distribution versus entropy
that that really is like the Shannon
entropy where
um the entropy like if it's if there's
a high probability it's low entropy
right but if they're like so so I look
at this in a coin flip so if we know
that the coin is always going to come
out heads there's not any entropy in
that like say it's a two-sided head coin
so like it's always going to come out
heads there's no other options the coin
always flips heads but where in a Fair
coin it's 50 50 right so like at the um
right end of the second graph it's a
probability of 0.5.5 like half of
probability that it's heads in half of a
probability that it's Tails this has the
highest entropy because it's random like
we don't know what's going to come out
and so that is what is meant here by um
information theoretic entropy
in contrast to thermodynamic entropy
um where that is like what we think
about when we think about physics and
the second law of Thermodynamics entropy
we think entropy in the universe is
always increasing there's like a lot of
like disorder the disorder in the
universe like if you clean your house
and you go away for 20 years and you
come back and your house is a mess like
you're not going to be surprised at all
right but if you if you if your house is
a mess and you go away for 20 years and
you come back and your house is
perfectly spotless like that would be
weird right but like that's like you you
know scheduled for someone to come in
and clean it but but like the disorder
in the universe is always increasing I
mean that that is what is meant by
entropy in terms of
um the second law and we also think
about this kind of entropy as energy
this is where Tyler and I got into
talking about energy but it's the
entropy the entropy is the energy that
is not available to do work right so so
in
um in a system there's like some amount
of energy like I you know can consumed
so many calories in a day and this is
like very simplified but of those
calories like I'd say I consumed 2 000
calories in a day I can use only like
1500 of them for work because some
energy is always lost in heat in the
conversion in any energy conversion
process like converting energy to work
you will always lose some energy as heat
and so that is kind of another way to
think about this thermodynamic entropy
um Tyler were you able to find that
quote where we've talked about this or
no yeah it was the quote is is fairly
subtle in that he goes right between
information
um information Theory and thermodynamic
Theory kind of seamlessly and he doesn't
make it clear that these are like two
very different different things that
there's a potential tenuous connection
between so he says fep hence has no
purpose of its own it Powers it
generally the generative process of
active inactive inference is dedicated
to minimizing the information
theoretical maximal difference between
the top-down predictions and the action
generated bottom-up stimuli and pursuit
of many Rising areas of President
entropy variational free energy and
thermodynamic free energy are inversely
related variational free energy side and
thermodynamic entropy will be high and
thermodynamic free energy the energy
available for doing productive work will
be low so I think what you did there was
like subtle he like just goes between
informational and thermodynamic energy
kind of interchangeably and they were
like wait a minute there's like actually
a difference between these two concepts
and a connection between them is
something that you know active the
community doesn't have a great handle on
at this point
very cool uh Daniel do you have any
comments there on that
it's a pretty complex and developing
area how the informational entropy is
related to the actual
physics and biology it's kind of like
the connection between
friston free energy and Gibbs free
energy how does reducing divergences on
informational spaces translate to the
amount of available energy and their
situations where survival could be
secured one way or the other there just
isn't at this point a general answer to
how they're connected
so so when Tyler asked me how how
they're connected what is the
relationship
um my answer is uh Maxwell's demon is is
the like the connection really between
thermodynamic and informational free
energy and there's actually like I think
a 2018 or 2019 paper that that
quantifies like this relationship
between thermodynamic and informational
entropy
um at the quantum level so I don't know
if that applies to all skills but it's
at least cool that and I don't remember
the paper off hands but if you search it
Maxwell's demon Quantum information
you'll find it I mean it's pretty recent
so it's it's neat that people are
thinking about like like concrete and
direct ways to transform
um and translate information theoretic
and thermodynamic entropy and so we just
kind of wanted to unpack that because in
that claim it was like whoa there's a
lot of a lot of things happening here
that it might be more useful for the
audience to have a a deeper
understanding of like what is known and
what is unknown and how how deep does
this Rabbit Hole really get go and right
so so it gets pretty uh pretty hairy
okay cool all right so back to reality
but back to things that we can
concretely talk about
so the reward signal so characteristic
of reinforcement learning is removed and
replaced with one sole purpose surprise
minimization
effectively the agent is empowered to
minimize Surprise by way of a generative
model of the partially observable world
only perceiving itself and the world via
outcomes
um and so like just for people who might
not be familiar with reinforcement
learning
um hold on just a second sorry
I am getting over getting over a
sickness sometimes I didn't want to
cough into the microphone all right um
so in reinforcement learning there's
like a couple required components so you
have a policy which Maps the state of
the environment to an action
um and that's like for an agent right so
this we're always talking about agentive
systems here so an agent has a policy
like if the environment is in this state
I will take this action and policies can
change and update and then there's a
reward signal which is given at like
each step so we're talking about like a
Time step type of thing second one I
take this action my reward is two carats
right so say my policy is to turn right
unless I see immediate Danger on my left
so so I turn right and I turn right and
I get two carrots I turn left and like I
can't turn left because there's media
danger over there it's against my policy
whatever
um so the reward signal is the number of
carrots that I receive right there at
that first step and then there's a value
function which actually tracks the
reward over time
um and the objective in reinforcement
learning is not to maximize the reward
signal at each instance but it's to
maximize the value function over time
and so in a circumstance like where I
turn right to get two carrots
um but like I could have gone down and
then right and gotten 50 carats like so
maybe I should have gone down and right
and so this kind this is kind of how an
agent will learn in a reinforcement
learning environment to maximize the
value as opposed to just maximizing
incrementally the reward
um so after every action that the agent
takes the environment sends a single
number that's the reward the reward that
the agent receives depends on the
agent's action and the state and so the
agent's only goal is to maximize the
total reward which is the value function
over the long term
any comments here
all right so Precision I'm Tyler do you
want to read the quote at the top of
this sure so the Beijing brain has
optimized its expectations it also has
to optimize Precision this means that
one has to predict how much Precision is
supported to various sources of sensory
evidence relative to Prior beliefs
thank you thank you
um and so this is like a definition from
Wikipedia talking about uh like
classifier systems and precision and
recall in a classifier system
um which is like a predictive system or
it could be Bayesian classification
so there are
um retrieved items like so we're gonna
say you know of this field of images the
ones in the circle are cats right so
we're identifying these circles the the
data points within the larger Circle as
all these things the the classifier says
these are all cats the Precision is
above all the things that the classifier
says are cats how many are actually cats
so it's the true positives that are in
um
in the system and then the recall is
like how many
total how many relevant items so that's
that's the the Precision here
um that's referenced by first
um do you want to read this one too
first Tyler sure all right so with
Dynamics change sailing should be
prevented from potentially increasing
free energy in the context of corporate
governance one may think of time
recognition as a one form of science the
more senior and experienced board
members are the more likely and they
feel comfortable with mental shortcuts
such as pattern recognition build repair
experience
foreign
I just randomly searched for like
pictures of salience to make this pretty
like red apple picture appear here
um but when I searched Salient and I
looked at images a lot of them were like
stakeholder salience and so I like
couldn't even start to try to unpack
this like it was some corporate
definition of salience and some
corporate model of salience that I don't
know if um Bhajan is referring here to
more indirectly or Tyler if you know
anything about like stakeholder the
stakeholder salience model but maybe we
could ask bijano if he um is referencing
that or if he's just talking about
salience the way that we talk about it
as in like things that we attune our
attention to because they're relevant
for the task at hand or like things that
stick out or things that are memorable
or relevant right yeah I don't think
there's like a corporate different
technical definition for me I think it
was just like you have limited attention
there are things that the port of it was
more likely to focus on and they have to
constrain their attention on limited
information
yeah but I was intrigued by the fact
that there is like a corporate salience
model like oh what is Bijan talking
about corporate salience what's that
um because it's just something that I've
never heard of before
well it's something we've seen with many
active imprints ontology terms that
there's a broad everyday qualitative
sense like salience is something that
you pay attention to and then there's
also a more technical usually Bayesian
sense such as salience is actually
referring to the Precision in terms of a
variance estimator that we place on
incoming sensory data whereas low
attention means that data points coming
in are not Salient they're not used to
update the model High attention is
coming together with high attention to
incoming data that does update the prior
a lot into the posterior and so which
patterns
are salience is itself learned and we
can think about that as the regime of
attention with all the strengths and
weaknesses the expertise and heuristics
bring along with
yeah and I think
um
they they go on to say uh they I think
Jean and Pat said more in the book
um about salience and pattern
recognition
thank you
okay so a single and double Loop
learning Tyler do you want to take this
single Loop learning occurs when errors
are detected and corrected without
altering the governing values of the
master program double Loop learning
occurs when in order to correct and
error is necessary to alter the
governing values of the master programs
most governance models are at best
single Loop rule-based learning systems
but struggle to activate double Loop
learning
thank you
um and I found this little like
Loop this Loop diagram which is like you
know actions and consequences actions
and consequences and that's like the
single Loop but um this double Loop
learning goes into understanding
governing very variables and like this
is kind of like I think about like meta
some kind of meta-analysis
um where you can you know it's zoomed
out more in the double Loop learning
yeah with our favorite example of the
temperature in the room
if the single Loop is just the knob that
we're controlling on the heater or the
air conditioning
the double Loop would be taking a step
back and thinking well could we also
open or close a window and so if we only
stayed within the single Loop maybe our
heater or cooler has limited capacity
and so there's times where the
environmental challenges
are going to take us outside of the
range of what can be learned or
accommodated with a single Loop and it's
those times especially when opening up
into a double Loop space or like a hyper
prior space is what is actually required
to get the generative model operating in
a way that's survivable
so like I would never open the window
with the heater on but boy like I
changed the weather stripping on my back
door this year and it made such a huge
difference so that's like a more a more
realistic uh like a governing variable
like you have a leaky house or poor
insulation or something like that
all right
uh deliberate ignorance so that is
choosing not to know
um so Bijan talked about this and says
the more senior and experienced board
members are the more likely that they
feel comfortable with mental shortcuts
such as pattern recognition built
through prior experience that's what I
was going to say earlier about this um
again I thought it was this next slide
but when um they talked about here uh
pattern recognition as one form of
salient
um but in this deliberate ignorance it
says uh it is a form of prior-based
heuristics or too often simply
deliberate ignorance however in a
discontinuously non-repeat game
environment pattern recognition without
maintaining sensitivity for small but
nonetheless transformative variations
put survival at risk therefore we need a
process and a measure of error that
optimizes survival hence action-centric
free energy minimization powering
inactive Ai and so I thought about this
like okay we're talking about like
corporate strategy so in pattern
recognition that's super useful for
something like a game of chess right
like so chess has like these are the
pieces these are the rules there's only
so many like ways that a piece can move
and yes it's super complicated but like
over time a master chess player can
start to recognize patterns in the game
or or like certain you know sequences of
moves that result in uh you know success
and so if you know those sequences of
moves that result in success that's
pattern recognition but but in a
non-repeat game like where the rules are
always changing and the pieces can move
in a different way like imagine now
we're playing 4D chess like where we
could go also like X Y but we can also
move in the Z Direction jump over pieces
and so forth like if you add an extra
Dimension those
um prior patterns that you knew for you
know X Y chess now doesn't happen right
like they're not they don't even apply
or aren't even relevant here so failing
to update like your your prior pattern
recognition is gonna not lead to
successful strategies yeah just to make
this like a little bit more concrete
like so like a very like common example
of this I've experienced is that like
sometimes when you're doing business
strategy and like the business is still
running and you might have customer
service claims incoming while you're
doing like this core business strategy
generally you want to ignore all these
customer service claims because that's
just like noise and you don't want to
pay attention to it it's going to
overwhelm you
um though occasionally you'll sometimes
hear some like very unusual customer
experience claims uh like that's that
kind of implies something much bigger
and much more serious is going on
systemically within the organization and
you need to have this like spidey sense
and this for those often used in
business settings like the Spidey ends
up knowing like oh wait like something
bigger is going on I need to switch
gears into being super micro rather than
being macro
um so I think it's a good example of
when you have to kind of like switch
your your model of like having
organizations working really dynamically
and go from deliberate ignorance to
choosing what information will be
selling to you
oh
okay and then sophistication which I
thought this was relevant I can't
remember the the quote that we that said
this again oh uh Bijan actually started
to unpack this in figure four um and he
said we alluded to sophistication back
in chapter one
um and this also applies to this like
double Loop learning So Sophisticated
inference is where you have
like many potential steps that can
um unfold and this also applies to the
principle of least action which we're
talking about which is like a decision
Tree Search right like if you're
standing here at step one you can go you
know which is like the top level here
you can go to any of these four points
um you know U1 U2 you through your u4 so
if you're here at the very beginning
stuff and then each one of these points
has their own Branch choices that you
can make and then each one of those
choices has their own choices and so
this is you know
um this sophisticated inference which is
unpacked um in this paper sophisticated
inference and then we've done on
different live streams
um here before also we didn't do this
paper but we did
deep effective inference I think that
was maybe also 17 13. I can't remember
um but a long time ago it was like a
2020 early live stream uh with Ryan
Smith so in this sophisticated model
it's unfolding temporarily through time
and this applies to both like the
trajectory when we're talking about
least action trajectories and also to
double Loop learning where you're
looking at like maybe governing
variables um over time
so he starts to unpack that here in this
chapter it goes a little bit more into
it than in chapter one
all right so now we're on the fourth
part of this claim uh we made it all the
way to them uh active inference should
provide the basis to set free the
collaborative human machine artificial
intelligence potential so integral to
The multi-intelligence Firm
and note those two separate like AI
um abbreviations
all right so Bajan makes the claim
social fields are not as real-time as
electrically charged and chemically
powered neural responsiveness but the
underlying logic and principles
nonetheless determine firm performance
and survival all living self-organizing
systems as is true for organizations
strive to reduce entropy in pursuit of
minimizing surprise but organizations
other than living systems are too often
trapped in what aguirus 1995 termed
skilled incompetence meaning that
organizations are programmed to deal
with error and threat in ways that are
counterproductive to their own
intentions not least because
organizations struggle with unlearning
and deliberately suppress subtlety
that's maybe refers back to that
deliberate ignorance that we talked
about
um earlier
do you want to talk here Tyler about
organizational becoming
yeah sure so I mean I just saw that last
slide like a couple thoughts on that I
think about one part that was
interesting about this was like you know
explicitly connecting free energy to the
firm which I guess that's the whole
point of this book but I think that's
actually quite a large claim to say that
firms also exhibit free energy uh and so
I just want to point that out but then
also I think in a really important
aspect for energy governance is the lag
between uh stimuli and action and action
stimuli where that is a lot larger in an
organizational space rather than
something kind of like a neuron for
example and that makes I think a lot
harder to like operationalize and really
understand free energy in like a firm
context as well
so the next slide that goes into
organizational becoming and so this is a
term he doesn't really Define explicitly
um throughout the the book but he does
mention it
quite a number of times which I think
it's worth calling out so he says
strategic renewal as organizational
becoming is categorical imperative of
being in the game
and so again he doesn't explicitly
Define this but I think what he's
implying is this idea of becoming as
like this like deeper philosophical term
that goes back thousands of years
where
the an organization isn't a static thing
or it's not something that becomes
something into an end state but rather
it is like a dynamic process and it is
always a dynamic process
um
and so yeah blue Danes you have anything
to add to this
you have the heraclitus
River quote which is a statement of the
dynamic
nature of becoming
and then in contrast we have being and
so people often talk about being and
becoming as a noun-centric and a verb
Centric way to describe something is
something
is
that's like being or is it becoming
which is more of a process based focus
and so he refers to it as the site of
organizational becoming not some sort of
ready-made tool that's going to be
but rather a process that will be
applied or is already being applied as a
distributed site of becoming
cool do you want to read this one too
Tyler sure so ffp is not supposed to be
craving the powers the system to exploit
uncertainty and complexity and pursuit
of performance and survival by way of
curiosity driven epistemic forging and
exploration correspondingly if the
energy governance is a Next Generation
Learning System designed for a
discontinuous world detaining The Firm
from dominant top-down Logics empowering
continuous strategic renewal through
purpose directed generative inferential
inferential inferential and
cross-hierarchical prediction error
minimization
nice and so I wonder here if
organizational becoming and like
strategic renewal I wonder if those are
maybe being used interchangeably
um we've talked about like strategic
renewal or like maybe strategic renewal
is like a fundamental like an
organizational becoming or
organizational becoming include
strategic renewal and other things I
don't know that's a good question for
Bijon who we will get to
um ask lots of questions of next week do
you have any additional comments here
Daniel or Tyler
okay uh free energy guidance I'll let
you take this one
all right so for energy governance
effectively transpose the active
inference framework to the firm and
adopts fep as a first order principle
underlying a new logical organizing
built around three core Dimensions so
structure hierarchy cognition
environmental enactment capabilities
sensing and sense making uh the
framework is centered around Crosshair
alternative processes of sensing and
sensor making to institutionalize
continuous strategic renewal as a matter
of inactive inference and pursuit of
firm uh performance and survival
each other
nice
so here we are at the the end of the
free energy principle chapter the end of
the um first section
um on the fep in the free energy
governance uh textbook looking forward
to having a good discussion with the
author next week
um do you guys have any final thoughts
on this section or chapter or anything
overall
I think a question to unpack is going to
be how does a descriptive theory of
every thing in free energy principle
help us make normative or even adaptive
decisions for ourselves and for our
organizations every single information
architecture or strategy that a given
group implements will be describable in
terms of the particular partitioning
into internal external and blanket
States they're all going to be
describable in terms of Bayes optimal
inference given some generative model
and incoming stream of data so how do we
take something that is kind of like the
number line it just is and it is neutral
and then proactively apply it
up to and including the last mile do
people need to actually know about
information entropy to be part of a
system that's designed with these
strategies in mind
or is there going to be some other way
to communicate and apply it so
how we actually move it to the space of
proactive decision making today and what
that looks like in different sectors and
for different organizations is really
exciting
awesome
well I'm also looking forward to reading
the next sections of the book and
um kind of going Beyond like the the
background section into like what's next
what is the the application
um and looking forward to bijan's
comments next week uh Tyler any comments
or
answer no all good for me looking
forward to next time
yeah me too
um so if anybody has questions please go
ahead and submit them you're welcome to
email them to us or um submit them here
in the comments uh but do it before the
11th which is when our meeting with
Bijan will be and if you want to
participate on the live stream and have
read the chapters in the book and watch
the live streams or one or the other
um get in touch okay thanks guys
thanks